A Finding Aid to the Giovanni Martino and Martino Family Papers, 1913-2013, in the Archives of American Art AAA.martgiov
Archives of American Art
Giovanni Martino and Martino family papers
1913-2013
AAA.martgiov
Archives of American Art
2.5 Linear feet
The papers of Giovanni Martino and Martino family measure 2.5 linear feet and date from 1913 to 2013. Giovanni Martino’s career as a painter, and to a lesser extent, his work with his brothers at Martino Studios, is documented though biographical material, correspondence, printed material, photographs, artwork, and one scrapbook. Also found are papers documenting the painting careers of his wife, Eva, and daughters, Nina and Babette.
Martino, Giovanni, 1908-1998
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 4 series.
Series 1: Giovanni Martino Papers, 1913-2010 (Boxes 1-2, 4; 1.4 linear feet)
Series 2: Eva Martino Papers, circa 1930s-2013 (Box 2; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Nina Martino Papers, 1942-2013 (Box 2; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 4: Babette Martino Papers, 1945-2013 (Boxes 2-3; 0.4 linear feet)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated in 2005 by Eva, Nina and Babette Martino, Giovanni Martino's wife and daughters and in 2014 by Nina F. Martino.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives’ Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Biographical/Historical note
Giovanni Martino (1908-1998) was a painter in Blue Bell, Pennsylvania. Martino and his six brothers formed Martino Studios in Philadelphia, where Giovanni worked as a graphic artist. Martino's wife, Eva (1916-2012), and daughters Babette (1945-2011) and Nina F. (1942- ) are also artists. Martino studied at the Philadelphia Graphic Sketch Club, Le France Art Institute, Spring Garden Institute, and Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts. He specialized in urban landscape painting and regularly exhibited his work in solo and group exhibitions. In the 1960s, the family moved from Philadelphia to a house in Blue Bell, where each member could have their own painting studio.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Giovanni Martino and Martino family measure 2.5 linear feet and date from 1913 to 2013. Giovanni Martino’s career as a painter, and to a lesser extent, his work with his brothers at Martino Studios, is documented though biographical material, correspondence, printed material, photographs, artwork, and one scrapbook. Also found are papers documenting the painting careers of his wife, Eva, and daughters, Nina and Babette.
Martino, Albert; Martino, Antonio; Martino, Babette; Martino, Edmond; Martino, Ernest; Martino, Eva Marinelli; Martino, Frank; Martino, Nina F.; Martino, William; Painters--Pennsylvania; Photographs; Scrapbooks
- Giovanni Martino Papers, 1944-2001; Series 1; 1.4 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, 4
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged as 6 subseries.
  1.1: Biographical Material, 1944-2001
  1.2: Correspondence, 1942-1983
  1.3: Printed Material, 1930s-2010
  1.4: Photographs, 1915-1990s
  1.5: Artwork, 1913-1980s
  1.6: Scrapbook, 1933-1959
  Scope and Contents note
  Giovanni Martino’s papers include scattered biographical material, such as awards and curriculum vitae; a small amount of correspondence documenting awards, sales, and exhibition of his artwork; and exhibition catalogs, news clippings, and other printed material documenting his career and the activities of the Martino family. Photographs include portraits of Martino as well as family photographs of Martino as a child, with his brothers, and with his wife and children. A few photographs depict Martino painting outdoors. Also found are figure and landscape drawings on paper by Martino. Some of his early drawings are signed with the alias “M. Giovanni.” One scrapbook contains letters, news clippings, exhibition publications, and photographs.
  - Biographical Material, 1944-2001; 1.1
    - Award Certificates, 1952-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Oversize material housed in box 4, folder 1
    - Biographical Material, 1950s-2001 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Oversize Award Certificates from Box 1, Folder 1, 1944-1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1983; 1.2
    - Correspondence, 1942-1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1955-1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Printed Material, 1930s-2010; 1.3
    - Book, The Martinos: A Legacy of Art by James McClelland, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Exhibition and Event Announcements, 1955-2005 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Exhibition Catalogs, 1937; 1940-2005 (Box 1, Folder 7-17)
    - Magazines and Bulletins, 1938-1947; 1994 (Box 1, Folder 18-20)
    - News Clippings, circa 1930s-2005 (Box 1, Folder 21-27)
      Oversize material housed in box 4, folder 2
    - Reproductions of Artwork, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Oversize News Clippings, 1955-2005 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, 1915-1990s; 1.4
    - Giovanni Martino and Others, 1915-1990s (Box 1, Folder 29-35)
      Oversize material housed in box 4, folder 3
    - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1930s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
      Oversize material housed in box 4, folder 4
    - Oversize Photographs of Giovanni Martino and Others from Box 1, Folders 29-35, 1928-1938 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Oversize Photographs of Artwork from Box 2, Folders 1-4, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Artwork, 1913-1980s; 1.5
    - Artwork, 1913-1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Oversized material housed in box 4, folder 5
    - Oversized Artwork from Box 2, Folder 5, circa 1920s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook, 1933-1959; 1.6
    - Scrapbook, 1933-1959 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Eva Martino Papers, circa 1930s-2013; Series 2; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  Eva Martino’s papers consist of awards, exhibition publications, and many news clippings documenting her career as a painter. Many of these publications are for group exhibitions with her husband and daughters. Also found are a few original ink drawings by Eva, personal photographs of her and her family, and few letters documenting her professional activities.
  - Award Certificates and Prize Lists, 1965-1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Drawings, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1971-2013 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, circa 1955-2003 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Letters, circa 1992-2002 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - News Clippings, 1953-2008 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Photographs, circa 1930s-2002 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Reproductions of Artwork, circa 1980s-2002 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Nina Martino Papers, 1942-2013; Series 3; 0.5 Linear feet Box 2
  Nina Martino’s papers include documentation on exhibitions, including a retrospective of her work entitled "Illumined Solitude," special events, records of her work as a student at Temple University, and awards. Also found are childhood drawings and ink drawings of figures and animals, as well as watercolor and ink illustrations. Photographs depict Nina as a child, with her family, and her artwork.
  - Awards, 1969-2012 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Biographical Information, 1942; 2012 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Book, Illumined Solitude: A Retrospective of Paintings 1980-2007, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Drawings, circa 1953-1957; circa 1970s-1996 (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, circa 1971-2012 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
  - Festival Programs, 1995-2000 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - High School Graduation, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Illustrations, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Letters, circa 2011 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Masters Thesis, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - News Clippings, 1955-2010 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts Benefit Auction, 2013 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Photographs, circa 1944-1999 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Poetry, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Scrapbook Pages, 1968-1973 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Temple University Records, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Babette Martino Papers, 1945-2013; Series 4; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 2-3
  Found here are the papers documenting Babette Martino’s career as a painter, including awards, professional correspondence, fellowship records, exhibition catalogs, publications, and a portfolio containing images of her work. Additionally, her papers include a few personal items such as her baby book and photographs depicting Babette as a child, with family, and at events.
  - Awards, 1957-2010 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Baby Book, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1969-2008 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Magazines, 2007; 2005; 1997 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Pew Fellowship, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Printed Material, 1971-2013 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Professional Portfolio, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook Pages, 1966-1970s (Box 3, Folder 6)